Guide to the Shirley Kubik TWA Hostess Collection 1957-1958 PM 3
New-York Historical Society
Shirley Kubik TWA Hostess collection
1957-1958
New-York Historical Society
Kubik, Shirley, 1934-2023
PM 3
1.5 Linear feet in 1 document box, 2 flat boxes
This collection consists of material related to Shirley Kubik (1934-2023) and her career as a hostess with Trans World Airlines (TWA) from 1957-1958. Included are photographs, training manuals, performance reviews, flight diaries and notebooks, dining menus, and two TWA hostess hats.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by format.
Biographical / Historical
Shirley Kubik was born in Cicero, Illinois on September 21, 1934 to Edward and Edna (Stepka) Kubik. After graduating from high school, Kubik competed in local beauty contests, winning several. In 1957, Kubik was hired as an air hostess with Trans World Airlines (TWA). She resigned from TWA in 1958 to marry Charles Ettner. Kubik died on March 18, 2023.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Ettner family, 2023.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material related to Shirley Kubik (1934-2023) and her career as a hostess with Trans World Airlines (TWA) from 1957-1958. The material was gathered by Kubik in the course of her employment.
Personal papers includes correspondence, recruiting and training material, performance reviews and memoranda relaying positive comments from passengers, and flight log. These logs, found here in both bound and loose formats, include date, flight and airplane numbers, crew names, destination and origin locations, arrival and departure times, and other notes about the flights on which Kubik worked.
Also contained in the collection is Kubik's TWA luggage tag and parking pass, and two of her TWA hostess uniform hats. There is some additional TWA ephemera, as well as some menus from restaurants and nightclubs Kubik visited during her career.
Other material includes twenty-five (25) black-and-white and six (6) color photographs of Kubik and her fellow airline personnel, along with magazine and newspaper clippings which provide some context for Kubik's experience as an air hostess in the 1950s.
Air travel; Airlines; Flight attendants; Occupational training for women--United States.; Women -- Employment -- United States -- History.; Clippings (information artifacts); Logbooks.; Personal papers.; Photographs.; Printed ephemera.; Training manuals.; Trans World Airlines
- Personal papers, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Personal papers, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Flight Diary, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Logbook, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs, black-and-white, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, color, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Periodical clippings, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- TWA ephemera, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- TWA parking permit and luggage tag, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- TWA uniform caps, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
- Other ephemera, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Menus and other printed material from restaurants and nightclubs, some with personal notes written on them.